<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Isaac Freund</title>
    <link>https://isaacfreund.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Isaac Freund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://isaacfreund.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2021 Year&#39;s End Status Update</title>
      <link>https://isaacfreund.com/blog/2021-years-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://isaacfreund.com/blog/2021-years-end/</guid>
      <description>Hello all! This is my first ever status update so I&amp;rsquo;ve ambitiously decided to cover all of 2021. In the future I intend to write these updates on a monthly basis and provide a bit more detail. Since so much has happened in the past year I&amp;rsquo;ll be leaving out a lot, but here are some of the highlights.
In January I spent most of my time on river, fixing bugs and implementing an experimental river-options protocol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing River, a Dynamic Tiling Wayland Compositor</title>
      <link>https://isaacfreund.com/blog/river-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://isaacfreund.com/blog/river-intro/</guid>
      <description>In the spring of 2020 I found myself hooked on Wayland thanks to sway but increasingly frustrated with the i3 style window management sway implements. I tried several of the other more mature Wayland compositors including hikari and Wayfire but didn&amp;rsquo;t enjoy them any more than sway. I wanted dynamic tiling window management similar to dwm but on Wayland and without dwm&amp;rsquo;s configuration through patching the source code approach.
As I had a newfound abundance of free time at home in front of my computer thanks to the global pandemic that was ramping up that spring, I decided to write my own Wayland compositor.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
